<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Return to the priests about Beverley for their advisement.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91711</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1185</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E727_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865928</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865928</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118184</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91711)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118184)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E727[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Return to the priests about Beverley for their advisement.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 30 1653".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pomroy, John. --  Faithful discovery of a treacherous design of mystical Antichrist displaying Christs banners, but attempting to lay waste Scriptures, churches, Christ, faith, hope, &amp;c. and establish paganism in England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118184:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Return to the Prieſts ABOUT <hi>BEVERLEY</hi> For Their ADVISEMENT.</head>
            <p>I Having received a printed Book, which is full of untruths and lyes, come out of the generation of Lyars and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and full of ſubtilty and treachery, to deceive the ſimple with their Witchcraft and Sorcery: But God hath diſcovered your deſign, and he will gather his Sheep and Lambs from your mouths, and you ſhall no more devour them: The Lord is come, and coming to teach his people by his Spirit, and hath poured forth his Spirit, and doth pour it forth, that his Sons and Daughters begin to prophecy, and do; which makes the Teachers of the world to rage, who never heard a word from the Lord, but ſpeak a divination of their own brain, which the Lord is altogether againſt, who have lived in the form of the letter, and not in the Power; men of corrupt minds, to reſiſt the truth, as <hi>Iannes</hi> and
<hi>Iambres</hi> did, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. When the Children of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> were to come out of <hi>Egypt</hi> they reſiſted, as they did in the time of the Apoſtles who had the form, but are reprobate concerning the faith: So it is now with the worldly Teachers, who are made Miniſters by the will of man, do reſiſt the Truth now as they did, having the Form, denying the Power; for the Power brings out of darkneſs, out of
<hi>Egypt,</hi> out of Pride and Oppreſſion, and ſhakes the Earth, and cleaves the Rocks, and<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118184:2"/>throws down the Mountains, and makes the ſeed to come forth, which is the marvellous Work of the Lord, which makes the Heathen to rage and full of fury to ſee the wondrous Works of the Lord brought forth.</p>
            <p>The Title of the Book is, <hi>A faithful Diſcovery of a treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Deſign of myſtical Antichriſt, diſplaying Chriſts Banners, but attempting to lay waſte Scriptures, Churches, Chriſt, Faith, Hope, &amp;c. and establiſh Paganiſm in England; containing an Examination of many Doctrines of the People called Quakers in York-ſhire, together with a Cenſure of their Way, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Items concerning the deſign of God, Satan, and Man: Theſe things recommended to the conſideration of them who are in good earneſt for Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friends, Your printed Papers are conſidered and weighed with them that love Chriſt, and they are found falſe, and you to be Lyars, uttering forth your unfaithful D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcovery; for you are the <hi>myſtical Antichriſt</hi> which you ſpeak of, and your deſign is treacherous and found falſe, and weighed in the Ballance and found too light: And as touching <hi>laying waſte Scriptures,</hi> it is your own condition, take it to your ſhame, for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not lye;</hi> there you lay waſte Scripture, and are blind, and cannot ſee, but are falſe Accuſers, and accuſe men falſly, and found Lyars, and the Scriptures are fulfilled upon you: The Scriptures we own, are ours, and ſtand for, and own to be fulfilled and fulfilling in us; but all you that make a Trade of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which were ſpoken forth freely, ſuch are ſlanderers of Chriſt and his Church, and lay waſte Scriptures, and both eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Paganiſm in
<hi>England,</hi> and have eſtabliſhed it, who know not God nor his Church, but have called a Steeplehouſe a Church, and ſprinkling Infants their Baptiſm, which they baptize into their Faith, into their Church, which there is no Scripture for. Now all people, ſee if this be not laying waſte Scripture, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing Popery, which God never commanded, and to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of this myſtical Antichriſt which hath long ſtood, but now God is coming to throw it down and uneſtabliſh it. Are not thoſe Antichriſts who walk contrary to Chriſts Commands, and term themſelves to be Miniſters of Chriſt who walk out of his ſteps? Chriſt Jeſus, when he ſpoke to the multitude, and to his<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118184:2"/>Diſciples, he ſaid, <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them; They are called of men Masters, and have the chiefeſt places in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, lay heavy burdens upon the people, ſtand praying in the Synagogues, devouring widows houſes;</hi> But Chriſt forbids theſe things, and bids his Diſciples not to be ſo, but cryed <hi>Wo</hi> againſt them; And ſuch are eſtabliſhed in the Land now, who would dethrone Chriſt if they could; And you are in that ſame generation which was ever againſt Chriſt, and as the Scribes and Phariſees, who would have dethroned him, and never could own him in that nature you dwell in who gave forth theſe printed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. And as touching <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> we do deny that which holds up ſuch things as Chriſt doth forbid, which is no faith nor no hope but of the hypocrites which ſhall periſh, and all ſuch hope was ever denyed with the Elect &amp; Faithful. And the worlds Church do we deny, which is a houſe of ſtone; but faith which is the gift of God, we own, which purifies the heart, which faith is but one, and who are of faith are of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and this we witneſs to be fulfilled, and not denyed: And Hope that purifies the heart we own, but the hope of the hypocrites we deny, which ſaith, He muſt live in ſin ſo long as he is here, and doth not purifie, that we deny. The Church of God we own, which is the Pillar and Ground of Truth, which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his own blood, which is without ſpot or blemiſh: But as to call a Steeplehouſe, a houſe of ſtone, a Church, is blaſphemy, and you that do ſo lay waſte Scripture; for the Church is in God, 1
<hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. And Chriſt did not come to redeem a Steeplehouſe, nor to hold up ſuch things, but to redeem his people from ſuch things that be carnal, which you Pagans now eſtabliſh. And as touching that we deny Chriſt, it is falſe, it is your own conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for read <hi>Matth.</hi>
23. and there you may ſee your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, walking in their ſteps which Chriſt forbids, Phariſee-like, and ſuch are Antichriſts, and there you ſhew your ſelves to be Antichriſts in the myſtery of iniquity, being called of men Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, when Chriſt forbids to call any man Maſter, or to be called of men Maſter: But that Chriſt we own who cryed,
<hi>Wo unto them which were called of men Maſters, and had the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies, and the uppermoſt rooms at Feaſts, and greetings and ſalutations in the Markets,</hi> which the Lord Jeſus
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118184:3"/>Chriſt cryed <hi>Wo</hi> againſt, and taught his Diſciples not to be ſo; But all ſuch as hold up theſe things which Chriſt forbids, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which he did deny. Praiſed be the Lord God, who hath given us the light to ſee your abominations, and led us from your ſnares, which cauſeth you miſchievous men to vent forth your miſchief againſt the Truth, and utter forth your folly; but as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith, ſo are fools known, who are at <hi>Beverley;</hi> but God Almighty be praiſed, who hath given us a ſight to ſee your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, and to comprehend you who are deceived and would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; but your formal ways are layd open, and your ſhame and nakedneſs doth appear, and to us it is very ſerviceable, that you have put your folly in print, and do publiſh it abroad, who are not come yet ſo far as <hi>Balaam,</hi> who the dumb Aſs reproved; and the Angel of the Lord is coming to ſtop your way, though for a while you may rage and lye; but I ſay the Lord will rebuke that lying ſpirit, for a lying ſpirit the Lord doth abhor, for it is an abomination to him; it would make diſcord, but the Spirit of Truth doth diſcover it, and hath found you out to be of your father the Devil, who was a Lyar from the beginning; and for ſhame bluſh, and never make a profeſſion of Chriſt, of Faith, or of Hope, who openly have ſhewed your ſelves to be Lyars and Slanderers of the only people of God, who live in hope and faith, and in the fear of God: but it is that the Scripture may be fulfill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Lyars, curſed children, evil beaſts, and ſlow bellies, who ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own bellies, ſuch are they who cauſe the Truth to be evil ſpoken of, who are Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, glory in their ſhame, and mind earthly things, as ye may ſee <hi>England</hi> at this preſent time is full of ſuch Teachers and Prophets, which walk contrary to all the Commands of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which <hi>go after the ways of Cain</hi> to envy, and <hi>run greedily after the error of Balaam</hi> for gifts and rewards, <hi>who periſhed in the gain-ſaying of Corah:</hi> And there is your portions and conditions of the Engliſh Church, held up by you the Engliſh Teachers who gave forth this Book, who are made by the will of man; and thoſe who are come to the Church of God, which you call
<hi>Quakers,</hi> deny ſuch. <hi>Moſes</hi> did fear and quake, and the Apoſtle brought him as an Example to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> who were <hi>come to the general Aſſembly, and the Church<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118184:3"/>of the first born which is written in Heaven, and to God the Iudg of all,</hi> whoſe voyce ſhook the Earth, whoſe voyce now ſhakes the Earth, which makes you wonder and rage you earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded men, who never heard the voyce of God.
<hi>Moſes</hi> did tremble, <hi>Habakkuk</hi> did tremble, <hi>Iob</hi> did tremble, <hi>David</hi> did tremble and quake, and the Son of man was to eat his bread with quaking, and <hi>Paul</hi> did tremble that their faith might ſtand in the power of God, and not in the wiſdom of words; and
<hi>Daniel</hi> did tremble, and his ſtrength and breath was gone, and they who were with him did quake. Theſe Scriptures being fulfilled in the people of God now, ſuch you wonder at now, as they in the former ages who ſpoke forth the Scriptures were wondered at; And here you lay waſte Scriptures, and deny the fulfilling of the Scriptures, making a ſcorn of them and a deriſion, who are come to tremble as they did. Friends, you ſit as Judges to cenſure of their way whom you call Quakers, who are a people taught of God; you who are making bonds and ſnares to limit the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the holy One; in your own ſnares you are taken, and God will burſt them aſunder; for the Doctrine of Chriſt you know not, which is the Doctrine of the Quakers which you ſcornfully nickname; but that Word they own, elſe they ſhould lay waſte Scripture, as you do. But <hi>Moſes,</hi> who did tremble, fear and quake, did account it great riches to be reproached, and ſo do we with you in the ſame generation, who witneſs quaking, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did and <hi>Paul</hi> did; and ſo it is you that lay waſte Scriptures: and ſo you buſie minded fellows are cenſuring of the doctrine of the Quakers, ſhewing your ſelves to be thoſe buſie bodies who are ſpoken of in the Scripture, who have but a Cenſure, and no infallible Judgment; and ſo thoſe who have an infallible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will cry out againſt you to ſee your folly and ſlander.</p>
            <p>Whereas concerning the <hi>Deſigns of God, Satan and Men, and the dominion of Satan;</hi> There you are who gave forth theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, for Lyars you are of them which are of God: As you have uttered it forth ſhamefully, as in ſaying, <hi>they lay waste Scripture, Christ, Church, Faith, Hope,</hi> and in your concluſion you have but a Cenſure of the way and doctrine: Now all friends, who have a love to Chriſt, may diſcern and ſee your cenſorious ways, and give Judgment upon you who have no infalliable Judgment,<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118184:4"/>neither have Faith, Church, Chriſt, nor Hope, which the Saints do enjoy; but are without God in the world in their imitations and likeneſs, blaſpheming God and his Temple, and thoſe tender Lambs and harmleſs ones in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> who have been impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and perſecuted to death, who witneſs the fulfilling of the Scripture as they did who gave forth the Scripture: but the true God you know nothing of, nor the men who are of God, for you ſhew your ſelves forth to be Lyars of them who worſhip the true and living God: And this is to the ſtile of your Book, which is all falſe, and comes out of a falſe mind and a falſe heart, whoſe throats are an open ſepulchre, drinking up iniquity as the Ox drinks up water, who are of them who are the Deceivers of the Nation: But the witneſs of the Lord is gone out againſt you, and you are taken, and to Judgment you muſt come, for the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great Whore is come, and you Lyars muſt into the fire and lake that burns eternally; you ſhall witneſs what I ſpeak to be the Word of the Lord: And here I charge you in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord to be no Miniſters of the Goſpel, who are not able to give an infallbile Judgment, but only a Cenſure, which the Apoſtles had.</p>
            <p>Whereas you ſay, <hi>If in any age the Devil hath transformed himſelf into an Angel of light, or his Apoſtles and Miniſters have transformed themſelves into the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, they have done ſo in this Apoſtatizing age in which we live, yea they have been more cunning, ſubtil, and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſpiritual in transforming themſelves in this age, then ever they were in any foregoing Generation; Satan is now act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his part upon the Stage with all deceivableneſs of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and ſhall continue to act like unto himſelf, and beyond his former actings, until the Angel caſt him into the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pit, and ſhut him up, and ſet a ſeal upon him, that he may deceive the Nations no more; for by how much he ſhall perceive his Kingdom neerer unto a period, by ſo much more every day he and his factors will ſhew themſelves politickly active, for the ſupporting and exalting his helliſh and totter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdom: And as God hath, doth, and will enlighten his Saints and witneſſes more towards the end of Antichriſts reign, and the beginning of the calling of the Jews to Chriſt; ſo the<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118184:4"/>Dragon that old Serpent hath, doth and will more and more fill his Agents and Inſtruments with a Diabolical spirit of madneſs, and deluſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſhall ſtand for your ſelves, who have but a cenſure of their ways, who are called Quakers, and not an infallible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the Apoſtles had; and it's true, Satans Miniſters you are, who have transformed your ſelves to be like the Apoſtles and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt; but into their life you never came, nor never ſhall, but deſtruction you muſt know firſt. Have you not had the form long, and made a trade of the Apoſtles words, and Chriſts words, and the Prophets words, and would be like them, transforming your ſelves like unto the Apoſtles; but walk in the ſteps of the Scribes and Phriſees, who were enemies to Chriſt, which Jeſus Chriſt cryed wo againſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. who have been they who have <hi>crept into houſes, leading filly women captive, ever learning, and never coming to the knowledg of the truth,</hi> ſome Twenty, ſome Thirty, ſome Forty, ſome Fifty, and ſome Sixty years, and in the end never the better: The time hath been among you Shepherds and Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks on, <hi>The Watchmen are blind, they are all ignorant, they are all dumb dogs, cannot bark, lying down, loving to ſlumber, yea they are all greedy dogs which can never have enough, and they are Shepherds which cannot underſtand, every one looking for his gain from his Quarter.</hi> And here you are Shepherds of <hi>England</hi> about
<hi>Beverley;</hi> But God hath raiſed up a light in his People, as was in
<hi>Iſaiah,</hi> who cryed againſt the falſe Shepherds then, which light doth the ſame againſt you now, you dumb dogs who have but the letter, and not the word of the Lord, and do blaſpheme the Light of God where it is made manifeſt and dwels, which teſtifies againſt your deceits: And this is your <hi>Apoſtatizing age in which you live.</hi> Whereas you ſay, <hi>they have been more cunning,</hi> it is your ſelves who are ſo ſubtil and ſeemingly ſpiritual, in transforming your ſelves in this age (whereas you ſay <hi>themſelves,</hi> it is your ſelves) <hi>then ever they were in any foregoing Generation, Satan is now acting his part upon the Stage:</hi> Are not you them who pretend your ſelves to ſtand up for Chriſt, who hold up
<hi>Baal,</hi> and run after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> which all the Miniſters of Chriſt ſpoke<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118184:5"/>againſt, which Generation you are of? Who are they that are got up into the chiefeſt place in the Aſſemblies, and act as in a Stage-play, and have a glaſs to act their hour, and make a trade of Chriſts words, the Prophets words, and the Apoſtles words, and acts in the chiefeſt places of the Aſſemblies, taking a verſe and raiſing motives, tryals, uſes, reaſons and points from it, And then ſay the people, he hath handled his text well, and made good matter of it, and give unto the people <hi>Davids</hi> quak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, tremblings, weepings, prophecyings and prayers, and theſe are turned into meeter, and given to the ignorant to ſing, <hi>O Lord I am not puft in mind, I have no ſcornful eye:</hi> Here you are upon the Stage teaching people lyes, more ſubtil then in the foregoing generation; Satan acting his part upon his Stage with all deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, and ſhall continue to act beyond his former actings, ſo you may ſee who pretend and have pretended to be the Miniſters of Chriſt, have gone beyond all the falſe Prophets in the former ages, for <hi>Balaam</hi> who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs, durſt not take it; but theſe take it, you take it, and ſo you go beyond <hi>Balaam,</hi> he durſt not take it to curſe the people of God, but you take it which rail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people of God; and if they will not give it, they ſue men at the Law: And is not Satan here acting his part upon the Stage, contrary to Chriſt Jeſus and his Miniſters, who preach freely the Goſpel, who was beat and halled forth of your Synagogue?</p>
            <p>And as you ſay, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil the Angel caſt him into the bottomleſs and ſhut him up, and ſet a Seal upon him, that he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Nations no more:</hi> This Prophecy is upon your ſelves and the Angel is coming to fulfil it, and long have the Nations, been deceived by him that rules you, which is the Devil, into the bottomleſs pit he muſt go which you prophecy of, who are falſe Prophets, and will be ſhut up, that he may deceive the Nations no more, for now your Kingdom you are fearing, and you the Devils factors will ſhew your ſelves publikely active for the ſupporting of his helliſh and tottering Kingdom, for by how much he ſhall perceive his Kingdom neerer unto a peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od, he and his factors will ſhew themſelves more politickly active, as you declare it; but all your actings are diſcovered,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118184:5"/>and all your preachings are comprehended, and what they lead to; for take away your gifts and rewards, and then you will not act your part upon the Stage (as you call it.) And as God hath, and doth, and will enlighten his Saints, as you ſay, and witneſs more and more towards the end of your Antichriſtian Reign; God hath enlightened his Saints, and doth more and more towards the end of your Antichriſts reign; And ſee which light is their eye to ſee you the Antichriſt who hath long reigned; and as God hath, doth and will enlighten the Saints, and witneſs you more and more, you will all be found to be the Antichriſt, and blind Guides, who have long reigned upon the Earth, and brought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to perfection; towards the end of Antichriſts reign, little children, boys and girls will cry out againſt you, and the Scripture ſhall be fulfilled, <hi>Out of the mouths of babes and ſucklings the Lord will ordain ſtrength, and perfect his praiſe:</hi> And ſuch the Prieſts were againſt; and were not the Prieſts againſt Chriſt, and did incenſe all the rude multitude againſt him? and were not the Prieſts againſt <hi>Stephen</hi> when he was ſtoned to death? and were not the Prieſts againſt <hi>Paul</hi> who was a Tent-maker, and many to the Apoſtles fiſhermen? And ſo the Phariſees, then Enemies to Chriſt, ſtood up for their own Kingdom, when they ſaw it begin to totter, and Chriſt come to reign. The Phariſees and Prieſts had the form of Chriſt in words from the Prophets, but not the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. When he was come, they were the greateſt Enemies to him; So are you Antichriſt now, who have got the form of the Apoſtles and Chriſt, but not the power: Now your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is tottering, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is coming to reign, and be admired in his Saints; Happy day, happy day, doth the Reighteous cry, freedom from Antichriſt, freedom from all <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts alone by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And as touching the <hi>Calling of the Jews to Chriſt; ſo the Dragon, that old Serpent, hath, and doth, and will more and more fill his Agents and Inſtruments with your diabolical ſpirit of madneſs and deluſion:</hi> This ſhall ſtand for your own portion, for your Agents and Inſtruments with your diabolical ſpirit of madneſs and deluſions you have ſhewed forth againſt the Truth which is now riſing; ſo that old Dragon the old Serpent, hath and doth more and more fill you who are his, and ſo you fill the<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118184:6"/>ignorant, and would fill the Magiſtrate; but God be thanked who hath raiſed a light up in many of his, which ſees your abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations which you have committed: And the beginning of the calling of the Jews to Chriſt, which makes you unrighteous ones to rage, who are called out of your Kingdom: He is not a Jew who is one outward, which is in the fleſh, but he is a Jew who is one inward, that of the heart in the ſpirit, not in the letter, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God: And the calling of theſe Jews to Chriſt is dayly; praiſed be the Lord God for ever, who is encreaſing his Kingdom, which is not of this world. And whereas you ſay,
<hi>That whenſoever God hath drawn near to any Country or City in the light of his Gospel to expel Popery and Antichriſtian darkneſs, the Devil hath in ſuch Countries and Cities raiſed up a ſort of new and ſpiritual Antichriſts:</hi> You are the Antichriſts, belching forth your wickedneſs, who have got the form, yet live out of the life of Chriſt: As the Phariſees had the form of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the form of the Prophets; ſo have you Goſpel, but have put the Books, <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> for the Goſpel, which is the carnal letter, and a part of the declaration of the Goſpel, which Goſpel is Jeſus Chriſt the Lamb of God, which takes away the ſins of the world, which is glad tydings to every troubled Soul: And hence it is, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God hath drawn night to any Country or City in the light of his Goſpel to expel Popiſh and Antichriſtian darkneſs, which is your conditions; for you have had Chriſts words and a form, but walked out of his Command; but now the glorious light of the Goſpel ſhines, and you are all found to be Antichriſts, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the form, which is empty: For God hath in this age drawn near unto this Country, and his true light ſhines; and in Cities the light of his Goſpel is riſen to diſpel your Popiſh and Antichriſtian darkneſs, which hath long reigned, and layd cloſe, and kept all poor people in darkneſs. The multitude of proud and covetous Teachers that have been and are in this Nation, and the multitude of Sermons, what good have they done all this while? A Conſtable in his place may do more ſervice in keeping in Civilneſs, then all your Teachers in ſpeaking once a week to the people on the firſt day: and then in the week days, ſome in<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118184:6"/>the world, ſome to fighting, and oaths, and drunkenneſs, and ſome to their pleaſures, and the Prieſts often with them in the Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes; ſo that they do but obſerve that they call their Sunday, and come to the Idols Temple, and give him his wages, all is well. O ye deviliſh proud Prieſts, who are patterns of pride, which goes before deſtruction, God is coming to confound you all, and ſet up his Goſpel, which freely ſhould go abroad, for he hath ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you long to reign in Popiſh and Antichriſtian darkneſs; <hi>The Devil hath uſually in ſuch Countries and Cities raiſed up a ſort of new and ſpiritual Antichriſts:</hi> And there you are in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of iniquity and ſpiritual wickedneſs, not having the life of Chriſt, which have the form of the Apoſtles; But now the life of Chriſt and the Apoſtles is made manifeſt and riſen, which ſees your new and ſpiritual Antichriſtian darkneſs which is got up ſince the Apoſtles; ſo it is new, as in this age, but it is the old; and there you are the generation which was ever againſt Chriſt, who are far worſe then the groſs and Popiſh Antichriſtians, who live in the midſt of the Antichriſtian Babyloniſh Territories and Dominions, and are members of that Body, making War againſt the Saints and againſt the Lamb; but the Lamb hath got the Victory, praiſes, praiſes be to our Lord God Almighty for ever: And thou <hi>Babylon</hi> are become a habitation of Devils, and the Cage of unclean Birds; for the Popiſh Antichriſtians have many Idols, and Images, and Croſſes without them, and do not beleeve the overcoming of their ſin, but muſt have a Purgatory to be cleanſed in: So in Teachers near unto
<hi>Beverley</hi> are full of Images, having your Idol Temple without, which
<hi>Stephen</hi> was ſtoned to death for witneſſing againſt, which beleeve you ſhall never overcome ſin ſo long as you are upon Earth: Here you differ nothing from the Papiſts, but muſt have a Purgatory, elſe where will you be cleanſed? ſeeing no unclean thing muſt enter into the Kingdom of Heaven: And the light of the glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is riſen, and Chriſt is coming to overturn all your Popiſh and Antichriſtian Doctrine, which hath long reigned, but it ſhall not long have dominion over the ſimple ones. And as you ſay, <hi>The Sun is accompanied with divers Caterpillers and venomous creatures; ſo many venomous principles and practiſes have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered themſelves in the profeſſion and lives of ſome:</hi> This is<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118184:7"/>your own condition; for as Caterpillers you go up and down eating up the green, where it is ſpringing, as it ſpeaks in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation:</hi> And here in your paper of Adviſement you have made manifeſt, and as venomous creatures you are full of poyſon, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent-like, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. And ſo many venomous principles and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes have been diſcovered in your profeſſion and lives, which we cannot but teſtifie and cry out againſt, which is contrary to the Prophets and Apoſtles; the pride and oppreſſion that is held up by the profeſt Miniſters of the world, who go after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who bear rule by their means, who ſeek for their gain from their quarter, who are up in the chiefeſt places of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, which Chriſt and the Prophets cryed out againſt: and now Chriſt is made manifeſt, and ſends his ſervants to cry out againſt you and your venomous principles and practiſes, and have diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered your ſelves and your profeſſion and lives; this all people in <hi>England</hi> who dwell in the light will own what I ſpeak, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt your practiſe. Whereas you accuſe, That
<hi>Some in their profeſſion diſcover themſelves in their practiſes and lives:</hi> All unrighteouſneſs and ungodlineſs we do deny, and not juſtifie; But as the Summers Sun is coming, and the tender herbs are growing, you go like Caterpillers and Locuſts to eat them up; but the Weſt wind is ariſing which will drive you away, whoſe King over you comes out of the bottomleſs pit, and muſt return thither again: And as you do accuſe ſome of their lives, had you mentioned the fact, there had been honeſty in it; but all who are in the Truth will judg you here to be Back-biters, venting forth your malice; for no ungodlineſs do we juſtifie, but deny; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the world hate us, becauſe we teſtifie againſt the world, and the works of the Devil.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>Where the Goſpel hath gloriouſly ſhined for the enlivening and enlightening of others.</hi> True it is, you have had a glorious time as you call it, in making a trade of the declaration of the Goſpel in deceiving of others, Inſtead of enlightening, you have kept in darkneſs, where the Goſpel hath gloriouſly ſhined for the enlivening and enlightening of others, all your Witchcraft, and Sorceries are diſcovered, for God is enlightening and hath enlightened his, with the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goſpel, which light was, before the letter was, and the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118184:7"/>Lord is coming to make your Kingdom dark, who have ſet us Queens, and ſeen no ſorrow: Now your deſolation is coming, therefore your folly and madneſs you are venting forth. And as you ſay, <hi>Wherefore Solomon did apply his hearts to know Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Wickedneſs of folly and madneſs; ſo Chriſtians are not to be diſcommended who do endeavor to know miſtical errour of the New Antichriſtians which are riſen up amongſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This wiſdom is made manifeſt to the Church of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<hi>Solomon</hi> did apply his heart to know Wiſdom, we do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<hi>Solomons</hi> word, and the wickedneſs of your folly, and madneſs to us is diſcovered, ſo ſuch Chriſtians are not to be diſcommended who have put on Chriſt, and ſtand armed againſt your wills and deceits, who do endeavor to know, and do know the miſtical error of your new Antichriſtian Religion, which is the old Antichriſt, which is riſen up amongſt us that they may avoyd them. God hath enlightened his Saints, ſo that the true light ſhines in them, that your ſpirit is known to be the miſtical ſpirit of error, being in the way of <hi>Balaam</hi> you come to be denyed with them whom God hath raiſed, and ſuch you blaſpheme who are the Temples of God, and ſo the Scripture is fulfilled, The Beaſt ſhall blaſpheme God and his Temple: And you who have written your complaint abroad, and put it in print, and ſay, <hi>Some are riſen up amongſt you,</hi> God hath raiſed up a feed, thoſe ways which you cannot deſtroy with all your beſtical power. And as you deſire, <hi>That they may be furniſhed with abilities to declare againſt them, and the pains and labors of ſuch are worthy commendations, who by their Tongues and Pens do endeavor to lay open the Ridles and miſteries of Satan and his Inſtruments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you deceivers have contradicted your ſelves inſtead of giving commendations you give railing falſe Accuſations upon them who are furniſhed with abilities to declare againſt you, and the pains and labors of ſuch who lay open your Ridles and the myſtery of Satan, which rules you and his Inſtruments unto diſcovery, and hath diſcovered you to be both in
<hi>Babylon</hi> and confuſion that you may ſee it in papers, and ſhall ſee it more and more amongſt you; Some write, ſome ſpeak, ſome print,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118184:8"/>according as they are furniſhed with the abilities which God hath given them, to teſtifie againſt you who have long deceived the Nation, and have been the Inſtruments of Satan ſtanding up for his Kingdom; but now the glorious light ſhines, by which you are diſcovered. And as you ſay, <hi>Among whom theſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are to be juſtly and deſervedly honored, who have pithily, ſolidly and Chriſtianly diſcovered ſome of the Serpentine errors, and deluſions, and myſteries of the Familiſts and Quakers.</hi> In this here you Phariſees have juſtified your ſelves, and would be honored for your pithineſs, ſolidity and Chriſtianity, as you call it; but your madneſs and folly, and unjuſt dealing is diſcovered, and your Serpentine errors, and deluſions, and myſteries, which you accuſe ſome of the Quakers of; take it home, and judg your ſelves for there you ſhall find it, it is your own condition, portion and condemnation: all who are in the Light witneſs it with me. And as you ſay, <hi>Theſe Brethren are to be juſtly honored:</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren you are, but in the generation of the Phariſees, which was ever againſt Chriſt, as you have ſhewed by your conſulting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt his Spirit where it is, as the chief Prieſts, Scribes and Phariſees did: but all the righteous blood which hath been ſhed, was by that generation wherein you live; but wo is upon you who put light for darkneſs, darkneſs for l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, and evil for good; but wo is upon you and upon all ſuch who are covered, but not with the Spirit of the Lord, and ſtand not in his Counſel, but follow after your own imaginations, therefore have you uttered forth your lyes.</p>
            <p>And as you ſay, <hi>The bleſſing of him that dwelt in the Buſh be upon the endeavors of theſe brethren and proſper this ſmall Book, which hath much in it for the battering of errour, and the maintaining of truth according to Scripture; which is the prayers of us who can ſubſcribe our ſelves friends to all Saints; whoſe names are theſe I find ſubſcribed to this Advertiſement; Chriſtopher Feaks, Iohn Simpſon, George Cokain, Lawrance Wiſe.</hi> Whereas you ſpeak, The bleſſing of him who dwelt in the Buſh to be upon the endeavors of theſe brethren, and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per their ſmall Book; Him ye know not, who is the living God.
<hi>Moſes</hi> which ſaw him was a Quaker, and you ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deride ſuch who are brought into his condition now, and<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118184:8"/>Judg with your dark minds and evil thoughts them to be in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, ſo would ye do with
<hi>Moſes:</hi> So the curſes, and plag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, and vengeance of God will fall upon theſe Brethren (as you call
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) who have uttered forth their lyes and their errors; and that will come upon it, in ſtead of proſpering it, which you ſay <hi>hath much in it for the beating down of Error, and maintaining of Truth:</hi> In it you have ſet up the ſpirit of lying and the ſpirit of Error, as in ſaying we deny Chriſt, and ſo in maintaining of that which is contrary to Truth, which is a lying ſpirit. According to Scriptures I have proved you, for as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Lyars are without God.</hi> And as you ſay, <hi>which is the prayers of us who can ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe our ſelves friends to all Saints:</hi> The prayers of you Lyars are the prayers of the wicked, which are an abomination to God: And whereas you mention <hi>Saints,</hi> They are aſhamed of your practiſes, of your lyes, errors and blaſphemies, nor cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to you, nor none of your friends: Friends the Saints may call you, as Chriſt did
<hi>Iudas,</hi> and him that had not the wedding garment, who muſt go into utter darkneſs, and thither you are to go who are falſe accuſers and ſlanderers; ſo the Scripture is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled upon you who have wreſted and perverted them. And ſo much for your Adviſement.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
